Guide to the United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection OH.009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection
1975-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers
OH.009
7 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 2 compact disc boxes, and 3.5 cassette boxes.
1.7 Megabytes in 16 documents
The United Federation of Teachers is an American Federation of Teachers-affiliated union representing workers in New York City. The union was founded in 1960 following the merger of the Teachers Guild and the High School Teachers Association. In 1985, George Altomare, a founder and Vice-President of the UFT and history teacher, initiated an extensive oral history project to document the history of teacher collective bargaining in New York City. The union hired free-lance oral historian Renee Epstein to conduct the interviews with UFT members, organizers, staff, and officers. The interviews document the activities of the UFT and its predecessor unions, including the Teachers Union and the Teachers Guild. Also discussed are committees and organizing activities within the UFT and its predecessors, such as the Unemployed Teachers Organization, the Anti-War Committee, and the Communist Party's activity within the Teachers Union. Interviewees also reflect upon union leadership and the major strikes of the 1960s and 1970s, including the bitter 1968 Ocean Hill-Brownsville strike over community control.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of cassette 10 in box 5. Access to cassette 10 in box 5 is restricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 1985, the UFT commissioned Renee Epstein to conduct the interviews. They were deposited in the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives between 1985 and 1989. Audio materials that were not part of the 1985 project were later added to the collection. The accession number associated with this collection is 1986.022.
Arrangement
Access compact disks and transcripts are arranged alphabetically. Master cassettes have a numbering scheme that was applied to alphabetized tapes, with materials later added to the collection being given numbers at the end of the sequence.
Historical Note
In 1985, George Altomare, a founder and Vice-President of the United Federation of Teachers and history teacher, initiated an extensive oral history project to document the history of teacher collective bargaining in New York City. The union hired free-lance oral historian Renee Epstein to conduct the interviews.
New York City teachers first organized in 1912 with the publication of The American Teacher. The editor, Henry Linville, founded the Teachers' Union, which in September 1916 affiliated with the recently-founded American Federation of Teachers. The TU undertook the struggle to gain recognition and decent working conditions for teachers. It campaigned for fair appointment procedures, an annual salary paid monthly, minimum wages with gradual increases above the cost of living, and a sabbatical leave. In 1935, the Teachers' Union splintered over accusations of Communist Party domination. Rival factions disrupted meetings over political disputes and undermined the TU's unionist activities. That year, Linville and a majority of the Executive Board resigned and organized the Teachers' Guild. As one of its first acts the Guild created an unemployment committee to evaluate the Depression's impact on teachers. The committee found that only one in nine teachers was employed. Reduced class size would also remain a prominent issue for which the Guild advocated.
Additionally, the Guild worked to achieve recognition as negotiators for teachers who had grievances against the Board of Education. Frustrated by the confusion of having at least 12 different teacher associations during negotiations with the Board of Education, the Guild, along with the militant Committee for Action through Unity (including members of the Guild and the High School Teachers Association) and 1500 unaffiliated teachers, agreed to the terms of a merger. The new organization, the United Federation of Teachers, became Local 2 of the AFT. In 1961, the UFT won an election to become the sole collective bargaining representative for teachers, winning the endorsement of 77% of the city's teachers who were eligible to vote. In the winter of 1961, the UFT began negotiations on a wage and benefit package that had been submitted to the NYC Board of Education. Continued procrastination by the Board of Education precipitated a one-day teacher's strike on April 11, 1962, which resulted in a contract which became a model and spur to teachers throughout the country. After the Union's first contract, the ranks of the UFT grew to over 100,000 to become the largest union local in the U.S.
Related Archival Materials
United Federation of Teachers Records (WAG 022)
George Altomare United Federation of Teachers Audio Collection (OH 087)
New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection (OH 001)
American Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection (OH 008)
United Federation of Teachers: Italian-American Studies Committee Records (WAG 056)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of interviews with members, organizers, staff, and officers of the United Federation of Teachers regarding the activities of the UFT and its predecessor unions, including the Teachers Union and the Teachers Guild. Also discussed are committees and organizing activities within the UFT and its predecessors, such as the Unemployed Teachers Organization, the Anti-War Committee, and the Communist Party's activity within the Teachers Union. Interviewees also reflect upon union leadership and the major strikes of the 1960s and 1970s, including the bitter 1968 Ocean Hill-Brownsville strike over community control. Many of the interviews have been indexed or transcribed.
Audiovisual Access Policies
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Custodial History
In May 2021, the Carrie Cunningham interview was removed from the collection as it is part of the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection (OH 014).
Strikes and lockouts -- Teachers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Teachers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Teachers' unions -- Officials and employees -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews; Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Teachers Guild Associates; Teachers' Union of the City of New York
- Melvyn Aaronson, April 2, 1986; cuid407
  - Interview Summary (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 1A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 1A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_1
- Irving Adler, Jul 10, 1986; cuid408
  Scope and Content Note
  Subjects discussed include Unemployed Teachers Assoication, trade unionism history, and the NLB.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 2A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 2A-C)
- George Altomare, Aug 1985 and Aug 1995; cuid409
  Subjects discussed include Teachers Guild in 1950s and the UFT in 1960.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 3A-B, 56A-E)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 3A-B, 56A-E)
- John Bailey, Dec 30, 1985; cuid410
  Subjects discussed include merger, UFT organizing, and the 1962 election
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 4A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 4A-B)
- Yetta Barsh, Nov 21, 1986; cuid411
  Discussion of the UFT in late 1960s-1980s.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 5A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 5A-B)
- Simon Beagle, Dec 1982 - Aug 1985; cuid412
  Subjects discussed include socialism, the UFT and Vietnam, John Dewey, the American Federation of Teachers, and the Communist Party.
  Scope and Contents
  Some static heard occaisionally throughout
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 6A-E)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 6A-E)
- Mayor Abraham Beame, Oct 28, 1986; cuid413
  Subjects discussed include budget office during the 1940s-60s, strike, fiscal budget, mayoralty, and the labor movies of the 1980s.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 7)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 7)
- Sanford Blair, Apr 4, 1986
  Subjects discussed include collective bargaining, Al Shanker, picketing, organizing the UFT, and democracy.
  - Interview Summary (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 8A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 8A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_2
- Eugene Blum, Mar 25, 1986; cuid414
  Subjects discussed include colleagues' resistance to organizing and Al Shanker.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 9A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 9A-C)
- Charles Cogen, Jul 9, 1985 - Oct 26, 1986; cuid415
  Subjects discussed include Communist opposition, presidencies, collective bargaining, AFT history, strike, and merger.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to this interview is restricted.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 10A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 10A-B)
- Rita Cohen, Apr 17, 1991; cuid416
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 60A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 60A-B)
- Colby, Jun 27, 1989; cuid417
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 58A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 5, Cassette 58A-C)
- Ben Davidson, Aug 19-20, 1985
  Subjects discussed include criticism of Linville-Lefkowitz group, union relation to larger community, and the executive director of Liberal Party.
  - Interview Memoranda (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 11A-I)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 11A-G)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_3
- Jeannette DiLorenzo, Oct 19, 1985; cuid420
  Subjects discussed include the Teachers Guild's evolution and strike, bargaining coalition, and the evolution of the UFT.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 12A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 12A-B)
- Nathan Fein, Oct 21, 1985; cuid421
  Subjects discussed include socialism, Communism, restructuring the union in 1935, David Selden, and Al Shanker
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 13A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 13A-B)
- George Fesko, Feb 27, 1986; cuid422
  Subjects discussed include teaching, strikes, decentralization, and the UFT financial crisis of the 1970s.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 52A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 52A-C)
- Ray Frankel, Feb 17, 1986; cuid423
  Subjects discussed include organizing the Teachers Guild, the UFT's origins, and strike efficacy.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 14A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 14A-B)
- Samuel Friedman, Jan 6, 1987; cuid424
  Friedman discusses his life as a socialist.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 15A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 15A-B)
- Tess Gloster, Sep 26, 1986
  Subjects discussed include socialism, elitism, and grievances.
  - Interview Summary (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 16A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 16A-B)
- August Gold, Jul 11, 1985; cuid425
  Subjects discussed include organizing the Teachers Guild and the UFT and socialism.
  - Interview Summary and "The Board of Examiners vs. The Right To Think: The Case of August B. Gold" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 17A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 17A-B)
- Edward Gottlieb, Feb 1986 - Mar 1986; cuid426
  Subjects discussed include the Linville administration, the Great Depression, militant activities in the 1940s, collective bargaining, and integration.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 18A-E)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 18A-E)
- Louis Gregory, Feb 13, 1986; cuid427
  Interview includes discussion of Jamaica Evening High strike.
  - Interview Summary (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 19)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 19)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_4
- Allen Griggs, May 23, 1986; cuid428
  Subjects discussed include collective bargaining and grievance activity.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 20)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 20)
- John Hagan, Feb 19, 1986; cuid429
  Interview includes discussion of Teachers Guild in the 1950s.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 21)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 21)
- Louis Hay, Oct 31 - Nov 1, 1985
  Subjects discussed include socialism, Communism, democratization committee, and consulting work.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 34A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 34A-B)
- Velma Hill, Jun 1986 - Nov 1986
  Subjects discussed include integration, Congress of Racial Equality, and the Career Ladder Program.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 22A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 22A-B)
- Ponsie Hillman, Feb 25, 1986
  Subjects discussed include segregation, World War II, and joining the UFT.
  - Interview Summary (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 23A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 6, Cassette 23A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_5
- Hy Hirsch, May 28, 1986; cuid430
  Subjects discussed include socialism in 1920s, factionalism, the progressive caucus, the Dewey Commission, the CIO, and militancy in the 1950s.
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Access Copy (Box 3, Cd 24A)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 24A)
- Historical Documents, cuid431 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  Two folders of contextual documents created by the UFT or otherwise pertaining to labor or teaching. One folder pertains to interviewee Louis Hay.
- Sidney Hook-- Interview Summary, Oct 17, 1985; cuid432 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Subjects discussed include Communism in UFT and Dewey.
- Solomon Jaffe, Nov 9, 1985
  Subjects discussed include collective bargaining, Al Shanker, and the Special Education Program.
  Interview with Steve Cole.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 25A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 26A-B)
- Benjamin Kaplan, Jan 27, 1986; cuid433
  Subjects discussed include eligibles committee and collective bargaining.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 27)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 27)
- Israel Kugler, Nov 1985
  Subjects discussed include socialism, community college movement, and collective bargaining.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 28A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 28A-C)
- Abe Levine, Dec 24, 1985; cuid434
  Subjects discussed include 1950s generation and organization.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 29A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 29A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_6
- Sol Levine, Feb 18, 1986; cuid435
  Subjects discussed include UFT organization, caucus, politics, and CAR.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 54A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 54A-B)
- Martin Lobenthal, Jul 16, 1985; cuid436
  Subjects discussed include the Teachers Guild and the UFT from 1947 to 1971.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 30)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 30)
- Rubin Maloff, Jan 30, 1986; cuid437
  Subjects discussed include organizing the Teachers Guild, Communists in school, "business union," and bargaining.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 31A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 31A-B)
- Jack Mandel, Oct 11 and Oct 18, 1985; cuid438
  Subjects discussed include teaching during the 1940s through 1950s, salary, collective bargaining, strike, and supervising the in union.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 32A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 32A-B)
- Alice Marsh, July 5, 1985; cuid439
  Subjects discussed include activities from 1939 to 1960 and paraprofessionals.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 33A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 33A-B)
- Fred Nauman-- Interview Summary, Mar 24, 1986 - Apr 1, 1986; cuid441 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Subjects include joining union during the 1950s, decentralization, demonstration districts, and Ocean Hill-Brownsville.
- John O'Neill, Oct 27, 1985; cuid442
  Subjects include organizing in the 1960s, Vietnam, and paraprofessionals.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 35A)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 35A)
- Roger Parente, Aug 22, 1985; cuid443
  Subjects discussed include the High School Teachers Association, a 1959 strike, and merger.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 36A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 36A-B)
- Milton Pincus, Apr 7, 1986; cuid444
  Subjects discussed include the Teachers Guild in the 1950s, merger, and bargaining.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 37A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 37A-C)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_7
- Larry Robbins, Mar 28, 1986; cuid445
  Subjects discussed include the creation of the UFT, merger, goals, and strikes.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 38A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 38A-C)
- Bayard Rustin, Oct 29, 1985
  Subjects discussed include socialism, Communism and unions, assimilation, and paraprofessionals.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 39)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 39)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_8
- Dan Sanders, Nov 15, 1985; cuid446
  Subjects discussed include organizing the Teachers Guild and the Ocean Hill-Brownsville Strike
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 40A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 40A-B)
- David Selden, Jun 29 1986 and Mar 19 1990
  Recording of UFT Event.
  - Access Copy-- UFT Event (Box 4, Cd 55)
  - Original Recording-- UFT Event (Box 7, Cassette 55)
  - Original Recording-- Interview (Box 7, Cassette 57A-B)
- Al Shanker, 1985; cuid447
  Subjects discussed include new teachers' union negotiations and struggles with Board of Education.
  Interview by Neil M. Cowan.
  Audio on most of the access CDs has a muted/compressed sound which is often associated with multiple duplications. Tape #59E, which was transferred to CD #59E, had sticky shed syndrome and this defect has been carried over from the master to the access copy.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 59A-E)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Cassette 59A-E)
- Morris Shapiro, Jun 12, 1986; cuid448
  Discussion includes comparison of the trade teacher versus the academic teacher.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 42A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 42A-B)
- Rose Shapiro, Aug 7, 1986
  Subjects discussed include socialism, the Parent Teachers Association, the United Parents Association, the Public Education Association, and Al Shanker.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 43A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 43A-B)
- Harold Siegel, Oct 11, 1986
  Subjects discussed include socialism, the United Parents Organization, and the Board of Education secretary.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 41A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 41A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_9
- Fanny Simon, Dec 25, 1985 - Jan 1, 1986
  Subjects discussed include socialism, unionizing, Communism, radicalism during the Great Depression, Linville, the 1935 split of the Teachers Union and Teachers Guild, and AFT presidents.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 44A-C)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 44A-C)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_10
- Rebecca Simonson, Jun 1985
  Subjects discussed include Communism during the 1950s, federal aid, segregation, and integration.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 45A-E)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 45A-C)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_11
- Adolf Stone, Dec 23, 1985; cuid449
  Subjects discussed include substitute teaching and union motivation.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 46A)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 46A)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_12
- Morris Sukenik, Jun 21, 1986
  Subjects discussed include socialism, collective bargaining, and Al Shanker.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 47A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 47A-B)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_13
- Robert Wagner, Nov 1986 - Dec 1986; cuid450
  Subjects discussed include relationship with the Teachers Movement, Communist witch-hunt, trade union community, and the history of liberalism.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 48A-D)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 48A-D)
  - Partial Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_14
- Samuel Wallach, Oct 17, 1986; cuid451
  Subjects discussed include union activity during the 1930s, Wallach, and anti-Communist witch-hunts.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 49A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 49A-B)
- Sarah Wiener, Aug 20, 1986; cuid452
  Subjects discussed include Communism, decentralization, and the Retired Teachers Chapter.
  - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 50A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 50A-B)
- Ella Wolfe, Aug 17, 1985
  Subjects discussed include Communism, pacifism, and the Soviet Union.
  - Interview Summary (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Access Copy (Box 4, Cd 51)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 106, Cassette 51)
  - Partial Transcript, TW_OH_009_ER_15